All right, welcome back to 006 and our dynamic
programming quadruple of lectures. We are over
halfway through into lecture three of four. Today
we're going to follow up on this idea of problem
constraints and expansion that was mentioned
especially towards the end of last lecture. We saw
an example of subproblem expansion by a factor
of two in the two -player game with coins where we
wanted to have two versions of the game, one where
I go first and one where you go first. So this was
expanding the number of subproblems by a factor of
two. Today we'll see a bunch more examples of this
idea, including in one setting we've seen already,
which is Bellman Ford, which you can think of as a
dynamic program. Maybe it's a good time to mention
that Bellman invented dynamic programming in the
50s, same Bellman in the Bellman -Ford algorithm.
This was actually independent discovery by both of
them and other people. So he invented dynamic
programming, and then a few years later he applied
it to solve the single -source shortest paths
problem. So we saw them in the other order. We saw
single -source shortest paths first because it was
a little easier, and now we're seeing the general
framework that this fits into. And so we'll see
how that works. Why did Bellman call dynamic
programming dynamic programming? Mostly because
it sounded cool, and he was trying to impress
government agencies giving him grants. I mean, how
can you argue with something as cool sounding as
dynamic programming? But there is some logic to
it. Programming is a reference to an old form of
this word which means optimization, and generally
we're trying to optimize things. And instead of
optimizing according to some static kind of
approach or program, we're doing it dynamically.
This is a reference to the local brute force we're
doing to optimize at each stage. So you can't tell
at the top what you're going to do in the middle,
and so it's kind of each sub -problem is behaving
differently, and so in that sense, dynamic.
It sounds cool. All right, then we'll go to all
-pairs shortest paths. We'll see a new algorithm
for that that's not asymptotically any better, but
it's nice and simple and another cool
way to see sub -problem expansion.
Practical problems, parenthesizing arithmetic
expressions, and a real -world problem, piano and
guitar fingerings, so assigning a fingering to how
to play a piece. And we're going to do that with
our sort bot framework, so a quick recollection of
what that is. We define sub -problems, and we saw
how to do that for sequences. We try either
prefixes, suffixes, or substrings. We prefer
prefixes and suffixes because there's fewer of
them. If there's more than one sequence, we take
the product of those spaces. And then the idea of
what we're going to stress today is we can always
add sub -problems to make the next step easier. In
particular, adding constraints to sub -problems in
some sense lets us remember things about the sub
-problem that's calling us, or about the past is
one way to think about it, or in general, to
remember state. Just by adding more sub -problems,
we can remember more stuff, not just what things
we're working on, but some context. And that's
what we'll see lots of examples of today. It'll
hopefully make sense by the end of the lecture. We
need to relate these sub -problems with a
recurrence relation, which we usually just call a
relation. And the key idea here is to come up with
a question that if you knew the answer to that
question, you could reduce the sub -problem you're
trying to solve to smaller sub -problem solutions.
So this question is sort of the fundamental
aspect of some fundamental aspect of a solution.
Typically, when you're dealing with suffixes, you
want to ask some question about the first item, s
of i. When you're dealing with prefixes, you want
to ask a question about near the last item, s of i
minus 1. And for substrings, who knows? Somewhere
in the middle. We'll see an example of that today.
Once you have identified such a question, the
dynamic programming approach is don't be smart
about how to answer that question. Just locally
brute force. Try all possible answers to the
question. For each one, recurse and take the
best solution according to whatever metric you're
trying to do, typically minimization or
maximization. Another way to think of this local
brute force, which I like to think in my head, so
maybe some people like this, some people don't, is
to think about guessing the answer to the
question. So maybe the answer could be 0, 1, or 2.
And my algorithm will say, guess which is the
right answer. And I'll assume that my algorithm
correctly guesses the answer and analyze that.
So we can think of the program as going straight
through guessing the answer and then recursing and
then combining the solutions, however. But then at
the end, of course, we can't assume that the guess
was correct. In fact, we have to loop over all
those guesses. So it's the same thing, just if you
think of it this way, there's less looping in your
program. But when you analyze it, definitely the
loop is really there. You have to pay for all the
possible answers.
We like to make sure this relation is acyclic. We
get a subproblem DAG. And I like to specify an
explicit topological order to make that clear. We
have base cases for the relation. We have to solve
the original problem in terms of these
subproblems. And then we analyze the running time,
usually as the number of subproblems times the non
-recursive work in the relation. So recursion is
free because we're multiplying by the number
of subproblems. You can also sum over the
subproblems. Sometimes that gives you a tighter
bound. And then, of course, we also have to add on
the running time we spend in the original problem.
So that was a quick recap. Now, one problem we saw
in this framework two lectures ago, the first
lecture was single source shortest paths in a DAG,
which a lot of dynamic programs actually can be
reduced to single source shortest paths in a DAG.
In fact, the reverse is true. Single source
shortest paths in a DAG can be thought of. The DAG
relaxation algorithm we saw is essentially a
dynamic program where the subproblems are delta of
SV. The relation is delta of SV is the min. So
what are we thinking about here? We're guessing,
this is sort of a new phrase I want to add, we're
guessing, oh, actually, I wrote it right here, the
last edge, uv, on a shortest s to v path. So delta
of SV, the problem we're trying to solve is find
shortest s to v path.
And it's some path.
It looks like. But some feature of the solution
of this path we're trying to find is, well, what's
the last edge? It comes from some vertex u, unless
the path is of length 0. s equals v. That's a
special case dealt with in the base case.
Otherwise, there's some vertex u before v. We
don't know what it is, so we're going to locally
brute force or guess what the right answer is. So
look at all incoming edges from u to v. And
for each of them, take the recursive shortest path
from s to u plus the weight of the edge. So this
is the guessing or local brute force perspective.
And the reason this works is because g is acyclic,
and so it has a topological order. Otherwise, if
the graph has a cycle, and that's the case we want
to go to next, this recursive call from delta of
SV to delta of su will have loops in it. And so
you'll never evaluate this recursion. You'll never
finish. You'll never memorize. You'll be
sad. It'll take infinite time. So don't use this
algorithm unless you have a DAG. For DAG,
it's great. It's linear time. So that was a little
review. Now, here is single source shortest paths
in general graphs, which we know as Bellman -Ford,
but rephrased into the sort bot framework. So we
defined this problem in the Bellman -Ford lecture,
delta sub k of SV. Remember, this was the weight
of a shortest path from s to v that is restricted
to use at most k edges. This made the problem
feasible. We ended up taking the product of the
graph into all these different subproblems,
in fact. But from the perspective of dynamic
programming, we think of this as a subproblem
constraint. What we really want is the shortest s
to v path, but that's hard. So we're going to
break it up into smaller pieces for each k between
0 and v. We're going to say, well, let's think
about this problem restricted to use at most k
edges. And for simple paths, if there are no
negative weight cycles, we only have to go up to v
minus 1. We prove that, and
we know then we're happy.
But that's sort of the last thing we want to
solve. So if we look down at the original problem
we want, it's delta sub v minus 1 of SV for all v.
So if we could solve these subproblems, as we saw
with Bellman -Ford, we can solve the original
problem unless there are negative weight cycles,
and we use delta sub v of SV to check. Whether
there are negative weight cycles, I don't want to
repeat that, but that's all in the original
problem. And then we can take this relation that
we wrote for DAG shortest paths and just port it
over here. So remember, for a general graph, this
has cycles, so we can't use it because we're just
referring to arbitrary delta of SVs. So there's no
reason to expect no cycles there. In fact,
the call graph is exactly the graph g, so it has a
cycle if and only if g does. But now over here,
I'm writing exactly the same formula for this min,
but I added a sub k here and a sub k minus 1 here.
The observation being, if I've already guessed
what the last edge uv is for this path, then if
this whole thing has length at most k, then this
piece has length at most k minus 1. So I only need
to solve delta sub k minus 1. I have SV here, and
so that's what I wrote. Sorry, I have SU, what I
wrote here. There's one other thing, which is, as
I mentioned a little while ago, it could be that
we use fewer than k edges. And so let's consider
the case where we don't follow a last edge, and
we just add to this min the shortest path using at
most k minus 1 edges. That's one option for having
at most k edges. If we wrote equality here, then
we would remove that. Like the last problem
session. OK, good. So the key observation here is
that this recurrence does not have cycles. Just by
adding this index, if we solve these problems in
order of increasing k, all of the references from
delta sub k are in terms of delta sub k minus 1.
And so this is now magically acyclic. This is why
Bellman -Ford worked. But now, I think in a very
pleasing way, we're taking our graph that's
cyclic, and by spreading it out over various
copies of k and referencing always the smaller
one, we get an acyclic graph. Acyclic relations,
we have base cases like normal, and then we can
analyze the running time in the usual way, which
is summing. So how much does this cost? We're
going to take the cost of computing the relation,
which is the number of incoming edges to v. That's
this. Theta. And then sum over all subproblems. So
sum over k and sum over v. I wrote it as a
sum instead of our product, because this thing is
theta e.
The sum of incoming edges over all vertices is
exactly the size of e. And then we sum. There's no
k in this formula. So we just multiply by v, and
we get ve. So our good friend Bellman -Ford recast
kind of the opposite way. Before, we were
using relaxations. Now we're just writing the min
explicitly, but essentially the same
computation, just in a different order.
OK, cool. So those are reviews of old algorithms,
but in this new framework. Show how powerful it
is. Let's look at another example, which is our
friend. I'll write here. All pairs short as pants.
A few lectures ago, we saw Johnson's
algorithm, which solves this very well.
So one option we could use is just this same set
of subproblems, but for all u and v. So for u and
v and v, that's what we really care about. And
then we could say k up to v, something like that.
So this would work, but it would give the same
running time as running Bellman -Ford v times.
This is one solution we know, but not the best
solution we know for how to solve shortest paths.
So this would give v squared e,
which is at most v to the fourth. For dense
graphs, it is theta v to the fourth. So this is v
times v times e. But worst case is v to the
fourth. What I'd like to show you now is a
different way to solve this problem, almost
identical, but gives v cubed running time, which
for dense graphs is really good. So we're
going to reduce this 4 down to a 3. And this is an
algorithm called Floyd -Warshall. It's definitely
not an obvious algorithm. It's a very cool idea.
And it's a nice example of a different way.
Remember, this is subproblem expansion. We took
the problems we cared about and multiplied by
this choice of k. Here, we're going to do the same
thing, but define it differently. We're going to
define those subproblems differently. So first, I
want to number the vertices.
Starting at 1 for convenience. So c y. And then
we're going to define some subproblems, which are
delta, I'll call it u v comma k.
Maybe to avoid conflict, I will write a d here.
This is just a definition local to this algorithm.
So I want the weight
of shortest s to v path.
So far, just the same as the problem we actually
want to solve. This is delta of, sorry, u v.
But I'm going to add a constraint,
which is using only vertices
u v and 1, 2 up to k. So this is the divine
inspiration to define subproblems this way. It's a
different constraint than the one we saw here,
which was using at most k edges. So in some sense,
what's slow about this algorithm is that we have
to loop over all the incoming vertices. This is
expensive.
die auf der cetera. How about with 1 and 2 and
1 and 2 and 3, the same vertices? By label instead
of by counting them. Slight tweak, but it turns
out this speeds up the algorithm. So let me first
tell you how many
subproblems there are.
This is v cubed subproblems. Two choices for u and
v. And I have v choices for v, and v choices for
k, roughly.
So v cubed of these. But the key thing is,
that sounds like a lot, but the relation becomes
cheaper now, because I can just write delta u,
sorry, d of uvk is the min of two things, d of uvk
minus 1, and d of uk k minus 1 plus d of kv k
minus 1. It's a strange formula, because we're
using indices like k for vertices also, as well as
u and v for vertices. But we're also using k as a
counter. We can do this because our vertices are
numbered. So the idea is the following. We have a
vertex u, we have a vertex v, and we've already
found the shortest path that uses vertices 1
through k minus 1. That's what this quantity
is. So it could be, and now we're trying to add in
this vertex k and think about, what are all the
paths that could go from u to v using 1 up to k?
Well, it could be the shortest path from u to v
using 1 up to k doesn't use vertex k. That's the
first option. Just use vertices 1 up to k minus 1.
Maybe we don't need to use k. Or it could be that
the path goes through k. Well, it starts at u, and
it goes to k, and then it goes from k to v, all
using, for simple paths, if we assume there are
no negative weight cycles, and you have to run
Belmont -Ford to detect them. But assuming no
negative weight cycles, the shortest path from u
to v through k must start by using vertices less
than k, and then use vertices less than k again.
And that's what I've written here. It's from u to
k using k minus 1 up to k minus 1 labels, and from
k to v using labels up to k minus 1. OK? The cool
thing here is the min only has two terms, so this
takes constant time, non -recursive work. So this
is k is not on the shortest path, and this is k is
on the shortest path.
Cool. So this is constant.
Non -recursive work.
So if we jump ahead to the running time of this
algorithm, we get the number of subproblems, which
is v cubed, times the amount of work per
subproblem, which is constant. So that's just a v
cubed algorithm. For dense graphs, this is really
good. This is when e is v squared, then this is
the same thing as v times e, so as good as Belmont
-Ford. It's not as good as Johnson for sparse
graphs. Sparse graphs, remember, or in general
with Johnson, we got v squared log n plus v e. And
this is always vending v cubed. But it's
cool, because it's a very simple algorithm. Let's
quickly write the
topological order.
All we need is to guarantee that we solve problems
in increasing k order, because every reference
here is to a smaller k for the third argument.
And so, for example, you can just write a triply
nested loop, k equals 0, 1 up to v, and u and
v, and v and v. So if you wanted to write this
algorithm bottom up, you just write this
triple for loop, and then plug in this recurrence
relation here. And think of d as a table, as a set
mapping instead of as a function call. And boom,
in four lines, you've got your algorithm, except
you also need a base case. Base case here is
u v 0. So I have to define what that means. But
when k equals 0, the 1 through k set is empty. So
all I'm allowed to use are use my vertices u and
v. And so there are three cases for this. 0 if u
equals v. It's w of u v if there's an edge
from u to v. And it's infinity otherwise.
OK, but easy base case, constant time for each.
And then the original problems we want to solve
are delta u v size of v, because I number the
vertices 1 through size of v. And if k equals size
of v, that means I get to use all my vertices. So
that is regular shortest paths. This is assuming
no negative weight cycles.
OK, we already know how to do negative weight
cycle detection. So I'm not going to talk about
that again. But then this will be my shortest
pathways, because, yeah. I implicitly assumed here
that my path was simple, because I imagine that
I only use k once, 0 or 1 time. And that's true if
there are no negative weight cycles. Cool. And we
already did the time part of sort bot. So v cubed
algorithm, very simple. Basically, five lines of
code. And you've got all pair shortest paths. And
if your graph is dense, this is a great running
time. If your graph is not dense, you should use
Johnson, like you will. Or like you have
implemented in your problem set. Yeah. So how
would this compare to just running Dijkstra's
algorithm a bunch of times? Ah, what about using
Dijkstra? So let's compute. So running
Dijkstra v times is the running time of Johnson.
So running Dijkstra a bunch of times is great. If
your graph has only non -negative edge weights,
then you should just run Dijkstra. You get
this running time. And for sparse graphs, this is
superior. If you have negative edge weights, you
should run Johnson, which is Bellman -Ford once,
and then Dijkstra v times. And we're comparing
this to v cubed, which we just got. So this, I
mean, how these compare depends on how v and
e relate. So on the one hand, maybe v is theta e.
Sparse graph is quite common. Then the running
time we get here is v squared log v. OK, roughly v
squared.
On the other hand, if we have a very dense graph,
v is theta e squared, which for simple graphs is
the most we could hope for, then this running time
is v cubed. OK. So if v is near e squared, then
this is giving you v cubed anyway from the v
e term. So why not just use this algorithm? And
often you know a priori whether your graph is very
sparse or very dense or somewhere in between. If
it's somewhere in between, you should still use
Johnson's algorithm, because you're going to get
the benefit from sparsity and only have to pay
this v e instead of the v cubed. But if you know
ahead of time constant fraction of the edges are
there, then just use, or you have a small enough
graph that you don't care, just run a Floyd
-Warshall, because it's simple. And fast. Good
question. Any other questions? So this is an
example of subproblem expansion, a very non
-intuitive one where we use some prefix of the
vertices. But notice it's prefixes again, right? I
numbered the vertices from 1 up to v, and I took
a prefix of those vertices. So I just solved the
problem using prefix vertices 1 through k. So it's
actually a familiar idea. If all you'd seen are
all our dynamic programming examples of prefixes,
suffixes, substrings, actually it's a pretty
natural way to solve shortest paths.
Maybe even more natural than this.
Anyway.
All right. Enough shortest paths. Let's solve
two more problems that are more in our standard
wheelhouse. They will involve sequences
of inputs, not graphs. First one is arithmetic
parenthesization. So first
let me define this problem.
OK. We are given a formula with, say, plus and
times. Let me give you an actual example. 7 plus 4
times 3 plus 5. OK. Now, when you read this,
because you've been well trained, you think, OK,
I'm going to multiply 4 and 3 first, because that
has a higher precedence. And then I'll add the
results up. But what I'm going to let you do is
parenthesize this expression however you want. For
example, you can add parentheses here and here.
You must make a balanced parenthesis expression, a
valid way to pair up, or not just pair up, but
a valid way to evaluate this expression. Any
ordering you want. I could be inconsistent. I
could, for example, do this sum and then do this
product and then do this sum. OK. But some kind of
expression tree over this. And each one evaluates
to something. So this is 11. And this is 8. And
so this is 88. And my goal is to maximize that
computation. And I claim that this is the way to
maximize that particular example. OK. So let me
write it in general and get my notation
to match notes. So given a formula
a0 star 1 a1 star 2 a2 and so on up to star n
minus 1 an minus 1, where each ai is an integer,
as we like in this class, and each star i is
either plus or times. OK. So I'm using star as a
generic operator. It shows star because it is the
superposition of star on top of a time symbol. So
it's clear. Given some formula, any mixture of
plus and times that you like involving n integers.
And your goal is to place
parentheses to maximize the result.
OK. So you can try all the combinations here. If
I, for example, take the product of 4 times 3, I
get 12. If I do that first, I get 12. Then if I
add 5 and 7, I get 24. Which is less than 88. And
I check them all. And this one is the maximum
for that example. OK. So interesting problem.
It's a bit of a toy problem. But it's motivated
by lots of actual problems, which I won't go into
here. So to apply this framework, we need to
identify some subproblems. This is a sequence
problem. We're given a sequence of symbols. And
so the natural thing is to try prefixes, suffixes,
and substrings. I'm going to jump ahead and think
about the relation first. I want to identify some
question about the subproblem or its solution that
would let me reduce to smaller subproblems. This
is a little trickier. This is very different.
We're not always doing something on the left or on
the right. Or we can't assume there's something
happening on the left. Because maybe we take a
product in the middle first.
Then I have some result here. But I still have
three things. I have the thing to the left. I have
the thing in the middle. And I have the thing
on the right. And it turns out to be very messy to
think about what the first operation is. Because
we can think of this as a tree, where we take a
product here. We
take a sum of 7 and 4,
and 3 and 5 over here. And then take the product
at the root. But I don't know what the tree is. I
only know these numbers and these operators. But
I don't know how to organize this tree. And so the
idea is, if you think of this tree, what is the
one thing that's the easiest to identify? It's the
root. The root corresponds to the last operation
I do in this computation. The last thing I did was
take a product. And that's a lot easier. Because
if I guess who's at the root, which operator is at
the root, that naturally decomposes into the
left subtree and the right subtree. And those will
always be substrings. We kind of know this.
This node corresponds to everything left of this
operator. And this substring or this subtree
corresponds to everything to the right of the
operator. So this
is our idea. Our idea
is we're going to guess which
operation star i is evaluated last.
Or in other words, at the root.
So this is a question. It has n possible answers.
I guess, actually, n minus 1 from operator 1 to
operator n minus 1. And so we'll
just brute force all those choices.
So I wanted to start here to realize that if I
choose some star i in the middle, which might be
the right thing, like in this example, star i is
the middle one, middle operator, I naturally
decompose into everything to the left of
that operator and everything to the right of that
operator. This is a prefix. This is a suffix. So
you might think, oh, my subproblems are all
prefixes and all suffixes. But that would be
wrong. Because if you have a bunch of operators,
and say you choose
this one to be last,
so I have a prefix here and a suffix here.
And then there'll be some within this suffix, I'll
choose some operator to be the root of that one.
And I have a prefix and a suffix of this suffix.
But in particular, I will have to evaluate this
subproblem, which is a suffix, in other words, a
substring. So never use a mixture of prefixes and
suffixes. If you need both, you probably need all
substrings.
So our subproblems are
going to be substrings.
OK. I'm not going to write the subproblems quite
yet, because there's another idea we need. So what
do I need to do with a substring? So I'm going to
guess the middle operator and then evaluate the
left substring, evaluate the right substring. What
am I trying to do with those substrings? I guess
I'm trying to solve this problem, which is place
parentheses in order to maximize the result and
then return what the result is. And I can
use parent pointers to reconstruct what the
parentheses actually are.
So is it enough? The last operator is. Is it
enough to maximize the part to the right and
maximize the part to the left? Will that always
maximize my sum or product according to what this
operator is? And I think about it for a while.
Yeah, if I want to maximize the sum, I should
maximize the two parts. And if I want to maximize
a product, I should maximize the two parts. That
seems right. Except I didn't say that my integers
are positive. It's true if the integers are
positive. But to make this problem more
interesting, we're going to allow the integers to
be negative. So for example,
7 plus minus 4 times 3 plus minus 5. So I just
added a couple of minuses to a couple of the
numbers here. Then it's no longer best to pair
them this way. So if I pair them this way, like
this, or if I add parentheses this way, here, and
I get minus 2 here. So I get product of that is
negative 6, which is probably not the maximum.
In fact, I can do better, I believe, by doing the
left operator last.
So this is, I claim, the best parenthesis if I
remembered it correctly. So this is minus 2 times
minus 4 is 8.
Plus 7 is 15.
So I got a positive number, definitely better than
the negative number I got. And I claim this is the
best. And the key property here is when we take a
product of two negative numbers, we get a positive
number. So sometimes you actually want to
make things small, because small might mean very
negative. You take two very big negative numbers,
very small negative numbers, in other words. You
take their product, you get a very big product,
positively. So the signs cancel. So this seems
tricky. We want to work on substrings, but we
don't know whether we're trying to maximize. Or
you might think, well, maybe I'm trying to
maximize the absolute value. But that's not good.
Maybe overall, on this entire expression, I get
negative a million. And that's not what I wanted.
I wanted to maximize the sum. So I still need to
solve the max evaluation that I can get, the max
parenthesization. But I also need to solve the min
parenthesization. If I can solve max and min, I'll
know the entire kind of range that I could get.
And I really only care about min, especially when
it lets me go negative. But let's just solve, in
all cases, the min and the max, and then just
brute force the rest. That's what I'm going to
write down. So that was some motivation on why we
are going to define subproblems this way. So I'm
going to define x of i comma j comma opt to be.
Here is going to be either min or max. And this is
my subproblem expansion. I really just care about
max at the very end. But I'm going to care about
min along the way. And ij is going to specify my
substring.
So this is going
to be the opt value.
Opt stands for optimum here, or optimization. The
opt value I can get for the substring ai star plus
1, ai plus 1, and so on, to star j minus 1, aj
minus 1. OK. Being careful to get my indices
correct here. And I want 0 less than or
equal to i less than j less than or equal to n.
I claim and opt like this. OK. So I'm going to get
the min value and the max value separately. Those
are two different subproblems. That's my
expansion. This is the constraint I'm adding. And
I'm only focusing on this substring
from i inclusive to j exclusive.
OK. So I claim those are good subproblems.
Let's write down a recurrence relation.
So
I want to write x
of ij opt on the left.
And I want to optimize. So this will be min or max
on a set of choices. What is my set of choices?
Well, like I said, I want to guess what is the
last operation evaluated. I wrote star i here. But
star i is already defined. So I'm going to
use star k. So I'm going to guess which of my
operations between i plus 1 and j minus 1 is the
last one. And I evaluate. And that decomposes into
everything left of k. So that would be x of i
comma k comma something. And then we will do
operator star k on the part after
k, which is from k to j something.
And I'm choosing between I think it's i less
than k less than j. k is some operator in between
because I start at i plus 1 and I end at j minus
1. So those are the possible choices for k. I
tried them all. That's my local brute force. And
then I take what I can get on the left, what I can
get on the right, and multiply or add them
according to whether that operator is plus or
times. Now, should I maximize or minimize this
one? Should I maximize or minimize this one? I
don't know. So I'm just going to do more local
brute force. I'll say, well, let's just say opt
prime for the left. Or maybe I'll call it opt l
for left and opt r for the right part. And I'll
just add this to my for loop. Let's just try opt l
and opt r. Just take all possible choices among
min and max.
You could think hard. And for addition, for
example, if you're maximizing, you really only
need to maximize the two parts. And if you're
minimizing, you can prove you only need to
minimize the two parts. But for multiplication,
it's messy. And it could be really any of the
options because sometimes when you minimize, you
get a negative term. Sometimes you don't. And so
it depends what you're trying to do. You have to
consider all the signs. But we don't need to think
hard. We can just try all options. There's only
four choices for opt l and opt r among min and
max. You could do min min, min max. Max min
and max max. So it's just a multiplication by 4 in
this for loop. The big cost is actually this one
because there are j minus i choices for k. There's
a constant number of choices for opt l and opt
r. And you need to prove that this is correct. I
won't do it here. But the idea is if you're trying
to minimize or maximize your sum or product, it's
enough to know what ranges these could come in.
And the optimal choice will always be an extreme
in that range. And we consider all of them here.
And so we get this recurrence. Now, it needs a
base case. And we need to check that it's acyclic.
But topological order is just increasing j minus
i. This is the usual order for substring
problems because this is increasing length of the
substring. So start with very tiny substrings. We
just have an ai there. So that's going to be our
base case. And you grow up to the entire string.
And it doesn't matter how we order relative to opt
as long as we are increasing a j minus i because
i to k and k to j will always be strictly smaller
than i to j. And so this will be acyclic. The base
case is x of i, i plus 1, opt. This is always ai.
Doesn't matter what opt is because there's
no choice. There's no number in that substring
because we're exclusive on i plus 1. OK. And then
the original problem we want to solve is x of 0 n
max. Could also solve min and see how small
you can get it. So if you wanted to maximize the
absolute value, you could solve the max problem
and the min problem and take the largest of those
two options.
And how much time does this take? Well, how many
subproblems are there? For substring problems, we
have n squared subproblems. Now, we multiply
the number of subproblems by 2. But that's still n
squared. So we have n
squared subproblems.
And how much work per subproblem are we
doing? Well, as I mentioned, we're doing j minus i
choices for k, constant number of choices for opt
l and opt r. So this is theta j minus i, which if
I'll be sloppy, that's at most big O of n. And
it turns out to be the right answer anyway. So
there's linear amount of non -recursive work.
In fact, it's like a triangular number. But that's
still theta n cubed.
OK. Same running time as v cubed we just got.
But polynomial time. And this is pretty impressive
because we're really brute forcing all possible
parenthesizations. There are about 4 to the n,
exponentially many, parenthesizations of an
expression. But we're finding the biggest, the one
that evaluates to the largest value and the
one that evaluates to the smallest value in just n
cubed time, polynomial.
And a key here was subproblem expansion, where we,
in addition to solving the max problem, we also
solve the min problem. Because sometimes you
want to take two very small negative numbers and
product them together to
get a larger positive number.
Cool. Question? Would anything go wrong if I added
minus and divide? So what if I had operators minus
and divide? That's a good question. I'm certain
that minus should work fine. If we do min and max,
this will still evaluate the, should still
evaluate the largest thing for division. I need to
think about the cases. I would guess it works. But
what we need to prove is that the way to maximize
or minimize a division, say, given two numbers on
the left and right, is that it either corresponds
to maximizing or minimizing the thing on the left,
and then maximize or minimizing the thing on the
right. So as long as you have this kind of, it's
not exactly monotonicity. It's just that in order
to compute max or min, it suffices to know the
max and min of the two parts. It's like interval
arithmetic. If you know interval arithmetic, I
want to know what are the extremes I can get on
the output of a division if I'm given that a
number is in some interval here and some interval
here. If the answer is always use one of the
extreme endpoints here and use one of the extreme
endpoints here, then this algorithm will
work. Otherwise, all bets are off. Cool. So if you
negate, if you put a minus here, that will work
fine because it's negating this range. Then it's
just like sum. But oh, divide it to be careful
about zero. Yeah, actually. So it doesn't work
because we care about how close this can get to
zero for division. It might be enough to consider
those. It's like instead of minimizing and
instead of computing this entire interval, if this
interval spans zero, maybe I need to know if zero
is here. I need to know how close to zero I can
get on the left side and how close to zero I can
get on the right side. Still just four quantities
I need to know. I would guess for division that's
enough. Nice. Solved a little problem. So then
we'd be multiplying the subproblem space instead
of by 2 by 4. Hey, maybe we should put this on the
final. No, I'm just kidding. Now it's in lecture,
so we can't use it. But it's a cool set of
problems. You can do a lot with dynamic
programming. You don't need to be that clever.
Just brute force anything that seems
hard. And when it works, it works great.
And this class is all about understanding when it
works and when it doesn't work. Of course, we will
only give you
problems where it works.
But it's important to understand when it doesn't
work. For example, DAG shortest paths, that
algorithm on a non -DAG, very bad. Infinite
time. OK. Our last example is piano fingering.
So here we're given
a sequence of notes.
T0, T1, T for note,
up to T n minus 1.
These are single notes.
And all the single notes, all the single notes.
And we have fingers on our hands. This is not like
two -finger algorithm. This is the five -finger
algorithm. So in general, I'm going to assume an
arbitrary anthropomorphic object. So this is 5 for
humans, most humans. Some humans, I think the
maximum on each hand is 7. Could be smaller. Maybe
you've had an accident. OK. I'll solve it for
arbitrary f. And what we'd like to do is assign
fingers to notes to tell our pianist which finger
to use for each note. So normally, when you're
given sheet music, it just gives you a sequence of
notes you want to play. It doesn't tell you which
finger you want to play it with, unless you have
some nice training booklets. And they have a
little number on top of each. And I number them 1,
2, 3, 4, 5. And symmetrically, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5. And
so here's a giant piano for my giant hands. So if
Jason were here, he could sing these notes. So
maybe I play this with my first finger, my second
finger. Let's just say I'm doing a scale. So I can
walk. And now I think a typical way to do a scale
is to reach over with your second finger, I guess,
and then do something like this. No? OK. Clearly,
I don't know scales or how to play a piano. But
there's limits here. If I'm going from this note
and I want to go to another note over here, OK,
maybe I have a decent span from first finger to
fifth finger. But my span from my first finger to
my second finger is not as big. I can't reach as
far. So if I want to play this note and then this
note, I'd like to start here with a very extreme
finger on the left and then go to a very extreme
finger on the right. So I'm going to formalize
this problem pretty abstractly, because I don't
want to get into music performance. I'm going to
say that there is a metric, d,
for if I'm at note t with finger f, and I want
to go to note t prime with finger f prime,
then this function, d of t f t prime f
prime, gives me the difficulty of doing that.
The difficulty of playing note t with finger f
and then playing note t prime with finger f prime.
This w is width. So this is a transition
difficulty. I'm not going to worry about
difficulty of the whole piece other than saying,
well, I've got to play this note, then I've got to
play this note. And for now, just single notes.
You play a single note with your right hand, then
you play another single note with your right hand,
then another single note with your right hand.
Let's assume no pauses for now, no rests. And
great. So we have this difficulty from going from
the ith note to the i plus first. First note.
And then our goal is to minimize the sum of
difficulties. Minimum sum of d ti fi ti plus 1 fi
plus 1. And these fi's and fi plus 1 is what we
want to compute. We don't know which fingers to
use. We're only given which notes to play. So this
is actually a natural problem. There are lots of
papers about this problem. I've read a bunch of
them. Obviously not super well about how to play
scales. But there are notes like, or there are
constraints in this. Usually people write this
metric as a sum of different penalty terms if I
want to minimize difficulty. Difficulty is high if
I play a note far on the left. So if I go from a
low note to a high note, that's easier to do if I
use a lower numbered finger and go to a higher
numbered finger. You don't want to go, like I
was doing, from a high numbered finger to a low
numbered finger to play a note on the right.
That's annoying. So I'd like to do an assignment,
if I can, that avoids that. So I'll just have some
penalty of like 100 if that happens and 0 if it
doesn't happen. Sum up a bunch of terms like that.
Other examples are avoid the fourth and fifth
fingers, the weak fingers. Or if I'm playing a
portion of the song that is legato, then I don't
want to use the same finger to play two
notes right after the other. I've got to use two
different fingers for that. So you have a penalty
if fi equals fi plus 1, and these two notes are
not the same, and we're in legato mode, then we
add a penalty term. And things like that. I would
prefer, if I'm going from a very low note to
a very high note, I'd like to use more extreme
fingers, things like that. But we're just
going to assume this d function is given to us.
It's some polynomial size. If you imagine the
notes on your keyboard are n notes or m notes,
then some polynomial
in m size to this function.
So how do we solve this problem? I'm
running low on time, so let me give you
the idea.
And this is going to use
subproblem expansion.
So the subproblems are going to be x of i
comma f. This is the minimum total difficulty
to play a suffix, because I like
suffixes, ti up to tn minus. tn minus 1,
starting with finger f on note ti. So the obvious
subproblems would be without this constraint. This
here is a subproblem constraint. And you could try
to define the subproblems just as what's the best
way to play a suffix. But I claim it's important
to know which finger we start with. So we're going
to multiply the number of subproblems by capital
F, which is just 5, so a very small subproblem
expansion. And then we're going to constrain each
subproblem to say, well, what if I started with my
first finger? What if I started with my second
finger? What if up to the fifth finger? Try them
all. Then it turns out I can write a relation,
which is x of if equals the min. What should I min
over? I'll just guess this. I'm already told what
my first finger is to use, which finger I should
use for ti. So what's the next thing that matters?
Well, I guess what finger to use for the ti plus
1, the very next note. What is the next finger I
use? I will call that f prime and minimize over f
prime between 1 and capital F of the remaining
suffix starting with f prime plus my difficulty
function from ti comma f to ti plus
1 comma f prime, end of bracket.
So there's kind of a lot going
here. This is lowercase f prime.
But actually, if you think about what I'd like
to write the recurrence on, well, I start with the
suffix i. I like to recurse on the smaller suffix.
So that's x of i plus 1. And so here, if I know
that I'm parameterizing by finger number for i,
well, then in order to even call this function, I
need to know what finger I'm using for i plus
1. So once you decide on these subproblems, it's
really obvious you need to guess what is the next
finger and then recurse on that finger, recurse on
the remaining suffix of that finger. Now, why did
we need to know what these fingers were? Why not
just guess what the first finger is? Well, it
has to do with this difficulty function. For this
difficulty function, I know that I want to measure
the difficulty from ti to ti plus 1. And to do
that, because this function is parameterized by
four things, I need to know both the finger for ti
and at the same time the finger for ti plus 1.
If I remove this f, I could add a min over one
finger, but I can't really add a min over two
fingers. So what this does by parameterizing by f
here and writing down the optimal for
each starting finger f, I can, in some sense, I'm
remembering in this call what finger I started
with. Because I told it, you have to start with
finger f prime.
And so locally to xif,
I know what finger f prime is being used for
ti plus 1. And also, because of the definition of
xif, I know what finger I'm using for ti. And so I
get to know both of these fingers. One comes out
of this min, and the other is given to me as this
parameter. And then, of course, if I can solve
these problems, I can solve the original problem
by just one more min of 1 up to capital F of x0
little f. I don't know which finger to start
with, but that's just f choices. And so then this
recurrence gives me the overall solution. And I'll
just jump to the time. You need a base case and
topological order. But it is n f squared time.
There are n times f subproblems here. And for each
one, I'm doing an optimization over f choices. So
I get n times f squared. It's a polynomial. And if
f is a constant, this is actually linear time,
very fast dp. Now, what I described here is for
one hand, one note at a time. But you can
generalize this to two hands, each with one note.
Well, that's just 10 fingers. So you could solve
this separately for the right hand and left hand
if you know which notes are being played with left
hand and right hand. But some pieces, that's not
obvious. So to make it more interesting, what if
you have multiple notes at the same time? And
let's say, I think it's reasonable to say you can
only play up to f notes at a time, one for each
finger. And so you have an upper bound on
the number of notes at a time that we're playing.
Which is good. Oh, I have a drawing of this dp,
by the way, as a subproblem DAG. So this is the
original problem, which is we don't know which
finger to start with. But then we just have a
complete bipartite graph here, where we write on
each of these edges what is the difficulty of this
transition. The y -axis here is which finger
I'm using, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5. And the x -axis is which
suffix I'm considering, which note do I start on.
And so you could solve this with shortest paths in
a DAG, or you could just solve it directly with
dp, either top down or bottom up. OK, jumping
ahead. So if you do multiple notes at a time,
instead of this finger choice, which just had f
choices, we have, what do I write here, t to the f
possible states, where t is the maximum number of
notes that I can play at once.
And usually this is at most f, one per finger,
but we could generalize. And this is number of
fingers.
So I could deal with all 10 fingers of a typical
human set of arms, hands, and say there's at most
10. And so this is 10 to the 10. It's a big
constant, but it's constant, like a billion, 10
billion. But then it's that times n. And maybe
that squared times n will let me exhaustively
enumerate all the possible things I could be doing
with all of my hands. So you can apply this not
only to piano fingering, but also to guitar
fingering, also to rock band. Rock band is an easy
case where you just have five buttons and usually
only four fingers that you use. And this doesn't
really make any sound, so it's not that exciting.
So the case where f equals 4 is you can apply to
optimally figure out which finger, once you have
a difficulty function of what transitions are easy
and hard for rock band, then you can optimally
figure out your fingering for rock band songs.
With a real guitar,
this is a little bit harder.
And because there are actually multiple ways of
playing, or you can play different things. So in
this case, I'm going to play the same note. For
example, I can play the note of this string like
this. These should both sound the same. Because my
guitar were perfectly tuned, which it's not. And
that's properties of strings and the way these
things are played. So in addition to what finger I
use, I should also decide
which string to play that note on.
So for example, maybe I want
to play my favorite song here.
Super Mario Brothers, my favorite song. I could
keep going, but I actually can't keep going. It
won't be as impressive. I don't actually know
how to play guitar. But there are a lot of choices
there, right? I started with playing this note
down on this string. That's good. I could have
also played it on this string. But that's more
work for my fingers. So I have a different penalty
function that says, well, if I play an open
string, that's a lot easier. And then I had a
transition from here, this note, to this note, to
this note. And if you focus on my fingering here,
I chose to use my index finger for the first one,
because that index finger is always the easiest to
use. But it also gives me lots of room to move
my pinky over to here. And then I like to use my
middle finger to come up here. You could also use
your index finger. It's just a little bit more of
a reach. So you have to define some difficulty
function. It might depend on how big your fingers
are. You can do that and then optimize using these
algorithms what is the best guitar fingering for a
given piece, one note at a time or several notes
at a time. You could even add in parameters like,
oh, maybe I want to play a bar. That's not
a perfect bar. But this would be great for my
playing this note down here and this note up here.
Bad example. So you could do other things with the
guitar to make it more interesting and generalize
this dynamic program suitably. But I think this
gives you a flavor how, with subproblem expansion,
I can capture almost any aspect of a problem that
I want. As long as the number of states
that I need to keep track of is small, I can just
multiply the number of subproblems by that state.
And I can keep track of any kind of transition
from one state to another, which I could also do
with taking the product of a graph. But dynamic
programming gives you a kind of methodical way to
think about this by figuring out some property, in
this case the state of how my fingers are applied
to the instrument, and then just sort of brute
forcing the rest. A very
powerful framework.